Guide to the Mary Boykin Chesnut Diaries Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mary Boykin Chesnut diaries collection
1817-1886
MS 1263
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11
(15 boxes)
The collection consists of photoduplicates of original Mary Chesnut manuscripts, from the South Caroliniana Library at the University of South Carolina and from private owners, collected by C. Vann Woodward for the preparation of his book, Mary Chesnut's Civil War.
Chesnut, Mary Boykin, 1823-1886
Conditions Governing Access
The bulk of the collection is photocopies. No material in this collection may be photocopied without permission of the South Caroliniana Library and the owners of the Mary B. Chesnut manuscripts in that library. The only exception to this restriction is Prof. C. Vann Woodward.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of C. Vann Woodward, 1981.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series: I. Materials Relating to Diaries. II. 1860s Journal. III. 1870s Version. IV. 1880s Version.
Scope and Contents
The Mary Boykin Chesnut Diaries Collection consists primarily of materials collected by C. Vann Woodward, Sterling Professor Emeritus of History at Yale University, for the preparation of his book, Mary Chesnut's Civil War. (New Haven, Yale University Press, 1981). The majority of the collection is photoduplicates of original Mary Chesnut manuscripts, from the South Caroliniana Library at the University of South Carolina and from private owners. These photoduplicates were deposited at Yale University Library by Woodward with the permission of both the South Caroliniana Library and the owners of the manuscripts. However, no photoduplication of the materials in the collection may be made without the express permission of the South Caroliniana Library and of the owners of the original manuscripts. The same restrictions apply to the typed transcripts of the 1860s JOURNAL and the 1880s VERSION.
For biographical information on Mary Boykin Chesnut, see pages xxx-xlv of Mary Chesnut's Civil War, Elisabeth Muhlenfeld's Mary Boykin Chesnut: A Biography. (Louisiana State University Press, 1981) and pages 4-7 of this register. Woodward was awarded the 1982 Pulitzer Prize for History for Mary Chesnut's Civil War. Woodward and Muhlenfeld are currently editing Chesnut's 1860s diaries.
The collection is arranged in four series: The collection is arranged in four series: I. MATERIALS RELATING TO DIARIES, II. 1860s JOURNAL, III. 1870s VERSION, IV. 1880s VERSION.
Series I, MATERIALS RELATING TO DIARIES, contains Correspondence, Writings by Others, Articles, Genealogical Material, Writings by Mary Chesnut, Legal Documents and Accounts and Photographs. Virtually all of this is photoduplicates of Mary Chesnut material held in the South Caroliniana Library. A small amount is photoduplicates of Mary Chesnut material held by individuals, and there are a few original letters (Box 1 folders 29-32) from the 1970s pertaining to research on Mary Chesnut.
Series II, 1860s JOURNALS, consists of photoduplicates of the journals which Mary Chesnut wrote during the Civil War years or shortly thereafter and a typed transcript of those journals prepared by Elisabeth Muhlenfeld and Thomas E. Dasher. Series III, 1870s VERSION, consists of photoduplicates of an edition of the journals which Mary Chesnut prepared during the 1870s. Both the 1860s and 1870s materials have large chronological gaps. See Woodward, Mary Chesnut's Civil War, pages xv-xxix for a discussion of each version.
Series IV, 1880s VERSION, contains Various Openings for the 1880s Version, all of which are incomplete, a Rough Draft of 1880s Version, the Manuscript of 1880s Version and a Typed Transcript of 1880s Version. The originals of the photoduplicates in Series II, III and IV are held in the South Caroliniana Library.
The materials within each series are arranged in chronological order.
Editing; History -- Sources -- Publishing; Women; Confederate States of America -- Biography; Confederate States of America -- Politics and government; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives; Diaries; Chesnut, Mary Boykin, 1823-1886; Woodward, C. Vann (Comer Vann), 1908-1999
- MATERIALS RELATING TO DIARIES, 1817-(1860-1886)-1979; Series I; .75' (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - Letter of S. D. Miller to his daughter, [Mary B. Miller (Chesnut)?], 1835 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters from James Chesnut, Jr. to Mary B. Miller (Chesnut), 1839 May 9, June 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Typescripts of letters to Mary B. Chesnut, 1862-1863, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter to Mary B. Chesnut from Marie [Bad Weather?], 1865 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letter to Mary B. Chesnut from her sister Kate [Katherine B. Williams], 1865 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Typescript of letter to Mary B. Chesnut from Katherine B. Williams, 1865 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letter to [Mary B. Chesnut from Mrs. Jefferson Davis], 1873 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters to Mary B. Chesnut from Isabella D. [Martin?], 1874-1875 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Typescripts of letters to Mary B. Chesnut, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letterbook of Mary B. Chestnut, 1862-1863, 1876, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fragment of letter to Mary B. Chestnut from her mother, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letter from Mary B. Chesnut, 1850 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters from Mary B. Chesnut to her husband, James Chesnut, Jr., 1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters from Mary B. Chesnut to Miller Williams, 1874, n. d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Typescripts of letters from [Mary B. Chesnut?] to Miller Williams, [c. 1882-1883?] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Typescript of letter from Mary B. Chesnut to Mrs. S. Miller Williams, 1886 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Typescripts of letters from Mary B. Chesnut to members of Williams family, 1875-1876, 1882, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letters from Mary B. Chesnut to Mary Kirkland, ?March 31, June 15, n.d (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letter from James Chesnut, Jr. to President [Jefferson Davis], 1862 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Typescript of letter to [John Chesnut] from James and Mary B. Chesnut, [1865 or 1866?] (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Transcripts of letters to and from members of Chesnut, Williams, and Miller families, primarily to and from James Chesnut, Jr., 1817-1884 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letters to John L. Manning, 1840-1841 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letters to General G. W. Canty from G. M. Butler, 1841 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Typescripts of letters to members of Williams family, 1876, 1882, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Typescript of letter to Mary Harrison, 1885 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Typescripts of letters to Miller Williams and his wife Jane Williams, 1885-1886 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Letter from Isabelle D. Martin to David [?], 1905 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Letter from Harriet H. Ravenel to Mrs. Means, 1907 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Letter from Martha Williams Daniels to C. Vann Woodward, including reminiscences of Mary Withers Kirkland, 1976 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Letter from C. Vann Woodward to Martha Williams Daniels, 1976 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Notes by Elisabeth Muhlenfeld on various letters, 1979 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Letter to C, Vann Woodward from Martha Daniels, enclosing typescript of letter from Mary B, Chesnut, 1979 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Writings by others
    - Speech by Senator James Chesnut, Jr. before U. S, Senate, 1860 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Chesnut family history by James Chesnut, Sr., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Memoirs of Mary Williams, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Biographical sketch of James Chesnut, Jr., undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Articles
    - Typescripts of articles in The Charleston Daily Courier, 1861 September 26, 1862 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Obituary for Isabelle D. Martin in The State, 1913 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Genealogical material
    - Family genealogies for Chesnut Miller and Williams families, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Family genealogy for Whitaker family, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Writings by Mary B. Chesnut
    - Transcription of biographical sketch of James Chesnut, Jr., undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Fragment of manuscript "Two Years", undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Copybooks, 1838,1848,1850 (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
    - Manuscript fragment referring to Isabelle D. Martin, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "The Bright-Side of Richmond, Winter of 1864-Scraps from A Diary", undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "Let Sleeping Dogs Lie" [A family memoir and defense], undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - "Let Sleeping Dogs Lie; We have an author among us …", undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Fragment of memoir of brother who died at seventeen, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Memoir of sister Kate, n.y. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Legal documents and accounts
    - Typescript of will of James Chesnut, Sr., 1864 February 16 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Typescript of letters testamentary, proving will of James Chesnut, Sr., 1866 March 1 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Accounts of James Chesnut, Jr. as executor of estate of James Chesnut, Sr., 1866 February 4 - 1883 July 7 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Will of Mary B, Chesnut, 1886 January 28 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Codicil to will of Mary B. Chesnut, 1886 July 17 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Will of Isabella Donaldson Martin; notes on the will and the disposition of the estate, 1912 July 12; undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
- 1860s JOURNAL, Series II; 1.75' (2 Boxes)
  - Manuscript
    - 1860 November - 1861 Jul, 1861 February 18, 1861 February 25 - March 27, 1861 August 6 - 25, 1861 March 27 - June 27, 1861 August 25 - September 9, 1861 June 27 - August 3, 1861 September 15 - October 1, 1861 October 3 - December 8, 1865 February 4 - 23 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
    - 1865 May 7 - June 26 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Typed transcript by Elisabeth Muhlenfeld and Thomas E. Dasher (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Part I, 1861 February 18 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Part II, 1861 February 19-20 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Part III, 1861 February 25 - August 3 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Part IV, 1861 August 3 - September 9 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Part V, 1861 September 14 - October 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Part VI, 1861 October 3 - December 8 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Part VII, 1865 January - February 23 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Part VIII, 1865 May 7 - June 26 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Appendix, 1861 February 25 - 26 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- 1870s VERSION, Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  - 1861 March - August (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - 1864 Jan, 1864 September 21- December 8 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
- 1880s VERSION, Series IV; 8' (10 boxes)
  - Various Openings for the 1880s Version
    - Incomplete drafts of opening [original in purple pencil] (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Typescripts of incomplete drafts of opening (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Incomplete draft of opening (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Rough Draft of 1880s Version
    - 1861 September 9 - 1862 July 23, 1864 January 1 - February 6, 1864 March 14 - June 28 (Box 7, Folder 7-14)
    - 1864 July 6 - 1865 February 27 (Box 7, Folder 7-17)
    - 1865 February 27 - April 15 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Manuscript of 1880s Version
    - 1861 March 3-22, 1861 March 25 - April 15, 1861 April 26 - June 4, 1861 June 10 - July 19, 1861 July 22 - August 1, 1861 August 3 - September 19 (Box 9, Folder 19-26)
    - 1861 September 19 - November 25, 1861 November 27 - 1862 June 6 (Box 10, Folder 27-36)
    - 1862 June 7 - July 10, 1862 July 12 - August 1 (Box 11, Folder 37-40)
    - 1862-1863 narrative (Box 11, Folder 41-45)
    - 1863 October 27 - November 30, 1863 December 2 - 1864 January 1 (Box 11, Folder 46-48)
    - 1864 January 1 - 31 (Box 12, Folder 49-50)
    - 1864 February 5 - May 8 (Box 12, Folder 51-53)
    - 1864 May - sep 21, 1864 sep 29 - November 25, 1864 November 20 - 1865 January 16 (Box 12, Folder 54-58)
    - 1865 January 16 - February 27, 1865 February 29 - April 15, 1865 April 19 - July 26 (Box 13, Folder 59-66)
  - Typed Transcript of 1880s Version
    - 1861 March 3 - 1862 August (Box 14, Folder 67-84)
    - 1862-1863 narrative (Box 14, Folder 85)
    - 1863 September - 1865 July (Box 15, Folder 86-103)